<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ciheaturu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ciheaturu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-10T18:27:02+00:00</updated><id>https://ciheaturu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Remote sensing, forest dynamics, and geospatial data science for tropical landscapes. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Who Owns Knowledge? The Dangers of Parachute Science in West African Forest Research</title><link href="https://ciheaturu.github.io/blog/2025/Who-Owns-Knowledge/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Owns Knowledge? The Dangers of Parachute Science in West African Forest Research"/><published>2025-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ciheaturu.github.io/blog/2025/Who%20Owns%20Knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ciheaturu.github.io/blog/2025/Who-Owns-Knowledge/"><![CDATA[<p>In the vast tropical landscapes of West Africa, the forest is not just a carbon sink or biodiversity hotspot — it is home, heritage, and lifeline. Yet much of the scientific work conducted in these regions is often shaped by actors far removed from their realities.</p> <p><strong>Parachute science</strong> — the practice where researchers from the Global North “drop in” to conduct studies with minimal local collaboration or long-term engagement — remains a pervasive problem in forest research. The result? Data extracted without context, reports that fail to resonate locally, and recommendations that do not align with lived realities.</p> <p>But the issue runs deeper. It begs a fundamental question: <strong>Who owns knowledge?</strong></p> <p>Local communities and researchers in West Africa have deep, place-based understandings of forest dynamics, degradation patterns, and resilience strategies. These knowledges — rich, experiential, and often orally transmitted — are rarely valued on the same footing as satellite metrics or peer-reviewed outputs. This marginalization undermines not just epistemic justice but the effectiveness of conservation and policy interventions.</p> <p>Reframing forest research in West Africa requires a commitment to <strong>co-production of knowledge</strong>, <strong>equitable partnerships</strong>, and <strong>capacity building</strong>. It also means recognizing that mapping a forest is not just a technical exercise — it’s a political act.</p> <p>Let’s challenge the extractive legacies of environmental science. Let’s build research that listens before it measures, collaborates before it concludes, and shares before it publishes.</p> <p><em>This post draws on experiences from the SUSTAINFORESTS project and recent reflections on integrating local narratives with satellite observations.</em></p> <hr/> <p>Want to contribute your perspective? <a href="mailto:chima.iheaturu@unibe.ch">Contact me</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="forest governance"/><category term="parachute science"/><category term="West Africa"/><category term="forest research"/><category term="knowledge justice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on epistemic justice, power, and local agency in tropical forest research.]]></summary></entry></feed>